Guide to the Lloyd Richards Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lloyd Richards papers
1944-2004
JWJ MSS 176
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
94.25
(181 boxes) + 7 broadside folders
The Lloyd Richards Papers document the life and work of the director, educator, and actor Lloyd Richards. The papers consist of production files, professional papers, photographs, correspondence, programs, audiovisual and printed material spanning the years 1944 to 2004. The papers primarily document the professional life of Lloyd Richards through his production files, professional papers, and Eugene O'Neill Memorial Theater Center administrative files. Production files contain materials from all stages of production for theater, television, and radio productions directed by Richards, including those he drafted while Dean of the Yale School of Drama and Artistic Director of the Yale Repertory Theatre, and in a few instances for early plays that Richards acted in. Correspondence in the production files reveals the close professional relationship that Richards had with playwright August Wilson through directing six of Wilson's plays. Professional papers include files from Richards's service on various committees, boards, councils, and related activities; his teaching files from positions at universities and colleges; his speeches and lectures; awards and honorary degrees; clippings and printed material; and other papers related to his professional life. The Eugene O'Neill Memorial Theater Center material consists of administrative files and photographs that document his work as Artistic Director of the National Playwright Conference and his involvement in other Center activities. The papers also include correspondence with organizations and individuals, almost entirely regarding his professional affiliation with various theater projects. Photographs in the collection provide images of Richards, productions, award and honorary degree ceremonies, and other places and people. Audiovisual materials include film, video and sound recordings and film footage of productions, interviews, and other recordings of interest to Richards. A small amount of personal papers concern Richards's service in the U.S. Army Air Corps, his citizenship, financial and medical information, and other personal matters.
Richards, Lloyd, 1919-2006
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Lloyd Richards on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 2005, and from the Estate of Lloyd Richards on the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts and Letters Fund, 2007. Gift of Lloyd Richards, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
Boxes 149-153 and 161-167 (audiovisual material): ‡a Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm service copies are available for Series I. Production Files, A Raisin in the Sun program and prompt book (film number 3307).
Associated Materials
Printed material received with the collection was removed for separate cataloging and can be accessed by searching the library's online catalog.
Lloyd Richards (1919-2006)
Lloyd George Richards was born on June 29, 1919 in Toronto, to Albert George and Rose Isabella Richards. The family immigrated to the United States after seeing a flyer sent out by Henry Ford that advertised employment in his plant and settled in Detroit in 1923. Albert Richards died of diphtheria in 1928, leaving Rose to raise Lloyd and his four siblings alone. A few years later, Mrs. Richards was struck blind and Lloyd went to work to help support his family. Despite the difficult circumstances, all of the Richards children received an education and were urged to continue on to college. Richards entered Wayne University in Detroit and originally studied pre-law but he quickly shifted his focus to theater and radio drama. After graduating, Richards began volunteer service in the U.S. Army Air Corps, training with the nation's first unit of black pilots, the Tuskegee Airmen. Richards was never in active duty and returned to Detroit in 1945. There he co-founded the These Twenty People Company and The Actor's Company Repertory, and worked as a radio disc jockey for one year. He spent his nights and weekends working on productions and his days as a social worker.
In 1947, Richards moved to New York City to pursue an acting career. He waited tables and lived at the Y.M.C.A., focusing on auditions. At an audition for a one-man Equity Library Theater production, Richards met acting coach, actor, and director Paul Mann and studied with him until Mann asked him to become his teaching assistant for his actors' workshops. While Richards was a good actor and acted in several popular on- and off-Broadway plays, he wasn't considered a strong character actor and eventually focused solely on his directing. Mann's acting workshops would play an important role in Richards's development as a director. Through Mann, Richards met dancer and writer Barbara Davenport; they married in October 1957, and had two sons. He also met actor Sidney Poitier, who urged Richards to read and direct one play in particular, Lorraine Hansberry's A Raisin in the Sun. Richards worked hard to rally support for the production, and in 1959 the play debuted on Broadway in New York City to a standing ovation. The plot concerns an African-American family's experiences in a Chicago neighborhood and was the first play written by an African-American woman to be produced on Broadway, as well as the first play with an African-American director on Broadway. It is considered a landmark in American theater and social history. Richards went on to have a successful and prolific career directing theater, radio, and television.
In addition to his acting and directing in New York through the 1950s and 1960s, Richards returned to Detroit to direct summer theater at the Northland Playhouse (1955-1958), worked on radio productions, and opened the Lloyd Richards Studio for Actor Training in New York. In 1966, Richards was hired as Master Teacher of Acting at the new actor training program at New York University (1966-1972). From 1972-1979, he held the position of Professor of Theater and Cinema at Hunter College. In 1979, Richards was recruited for the position of Dean of Yale School of Drama and Artistic Director of the Yale Repertory Theatre, which he held until 1991.
When Richards was asked to be Artistic Director of the annual National Playwrights Conference (NPC) in 1968 at the Eugene O'Neill Theater Center in Waterford, CT, he took the opportunity to transform the conference into one of the most prestigious and intensive playwright opportunities in the world. NPC is where Richards met a young poet-turned-playwright, August Wilson. Wilson submitted work to the NPC several times and was rejected until he submitted Ma Rainey's Black Bottom in 1982, which gained him admission. Richards went on to direct five of Wilson's premieres, often at the Yale Repertory Theatre, and all went on to Broadway ( Fences, Joe Turner's Come and Gone, The Piano Lesson, Two Trains Running, and Seven Guitars ). Their professional relationship changed when they stopped working on Wilson's plays together, but the two remained friends.
At NPC, Richards mentored many young playwrights who went on to have successful writing careers, including Lee Blessing and Christopher Durang. In 1999, Richards retired as Artistic Director from NPC. At Yale, Richards directed and oversaw the premiere of plays that went on to tour nationally. Among these were Lee Blessing's Cobb, several of Athol Fugard's plays, and all but one of August Wilson's plays.
After retiring from Yale, Richards continued to teach in New York at the Actors Center and at the Actors Studio and occasionally directed. Throughout his teaching career, he was a visiting professor and lecturer at several universities and colleges. In honor of Richards's retirement, Yale University School of Drama created their its permanently endowed chair, "The Lloyd Richards Professor of Theatre Chair," and appointed him Professor Emeritus of the School of Drama. In addition to teaching, Richards gave his time and expertise to dozens of community theaters, professional committees, councils, boards, and fellowships. Richards received dozens of awards and honorary degrees throughout his career, including a Tony Award for Best Director for Fences in 1987 (he was nominated for a Tony several times) and a National Medal of Arts in 1993. He was admired as an influential director and educator, directing some of the twentieth century's most acclaimed actors.
While Richards worked and sometimes lived outside of New York City, he and Barbara considered the house on Manhattan's Upper West Side, where they lived since 1968, to be their home. Richards died in Manhattan on his 87th birthday of a heart attack.
Scope and Contents
The Lloyd Richards Papers document the life and work of the director, educator, and actor Lloyd Richards. The papers consist of production files, professional papers, photographs, correspondence, programs, audiovisual and printed material spanning the years 1944 to 2004.
The papers primarily document the professional life of Lloyd Richards through his production files, professional papers, and Eugene O'Neill Memorial Theater Center administrative files. Production files contain materials from all stages of production for theater, television, and radio productions directed by Richards, including those he drafted while Dean of the Yale School of Drama and Artistic Director of the Yale Repertory Theatre, and in a few instances for early plays that Richards acted in. Correspondence in the production files reveals the close professional relationship that Richards had with playwright August Wilson through directing six of Wilson's plays. Professional papers include files from Richards's service on various committees, boards, councils, and related activities; his teaching files from positions at universities and colleges; his speeches and lectures; awards and honorary degrees; clippings and printed material; and other papers related to his professional life. The Eugene O'Neill Memorial Theater Center material consists of administrative files and photographs that document his work as Artistic Director of the National Playwright Conference and his involvement in other Center activities.
The papers also include correspondence with organizations and individuals, almost entirely regarding his professional affiliation with various theater projects. Photographs in the collection provide images of Richards, productions, award and honorary degree ceremonies, and other places and people. Audiovisual materials include film, video and sound recordings and film footage of productions, interviews, and other recordings of interest to Richards. A small amount of personal papers concern Richards's service in the U.S. Army Air Corps, his citizenship, financial and medical information, and other personal matters.
Arrangement
Organized into seven series: I. Production Files, 1954-2003. II. Professional Papers, 1966-2002. III. Eugene O'Neill Memorial Theater Center, 1965-2001. IV. Correspondence, 1952-2002. V. Photographs, 1945-2004. VI. Personal Papers, 1944-2002. VII. Audiovisual Materials, 1962-2004.
Actors -- United States; Acting teachers -- United States; African Americans -- 20th Century -- Archives; Dramatists, American; Theater -- Production and direction -- United States; Drama -- 20th Century; Theater -- United States; Photographic prints; Theater scripts; Theater programs; Theatrical posters; Audiovisual materials; Motion pictures (visual works); Sound recordings; Actors; Directors; Dramatists; Fugard, Athol, 1932-; Richards, Lloyd, 1919-2006; Wilson, August, 1945-2005; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale Repertory Theatre; Yale School of Drama; Eugene O'Neill Memorial Theater Center; National Playwrights Conference
- Production Files, 1954-2003; Series I; 27.93; (53 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I. Production Files is arranged alphabetically by production title.
  Scope and Contents
  Files for each production listed may include prompt books; scripts; correspondence; contact sheets; contracts; financial and administrative records; casting files including actor resumes (sometimes accompanied by headshots); costume, lighting, and set designs, technical drawings, and related files; notes; research files; rights information; and posters, production programs and other printed material. The series documents the variety of roles Richards played in theater production during his career, including director, artistic director, producer, and actor. A small amount of correspondence concerning audience members' criticism and programs from various productions are filed at the end of the series.
  The bulk of the correspondence is with Richards's lawyer, Albert I. DaSilva. Correspondence with August Wilson is almost always present in production files for plays written by Wilson.
  Production cities, theaters and dates (when known) are listed under production titles. Station names are noted when a production aired on television.
  Photographs of productions are found in Series V. Photographs. Audiovisual materials relating to productions are in Series VII. Audiovisual Materials.
  - About William by H. Denker, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Includes correspondence with ATU Productions, Inc and Charles Adams
  - Aftermath, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    For television
  - Amen Corner by James Baldwin, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4-10)
    U.S. State Department tour of Israel and Europe
    Includes correspondence with Rudolf M. Stoiber
  - The Antique Bearers by Ray Aranha, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
    Earplay series, National Public Radio, 1978
  - Bedford Forest by Joel Oliansky, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13-17)
    Eugene O'Neill Memorial Theater, 1966
  - Blood Knot by Athol Fugard, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    John Golden Theatre, New York City, 1985.
  - The Book of Murder by Ron Cowen, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    ABC World Entertainment, Universal Studios (television)
  - Cat on A Hot Tin Roof by Tennessee Williams, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 20-23)
  - Christopher Columbus by Nicos Kazantzakis, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 24-27)
  - Christopher Columbus by Nicos Kazantzakis, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 28-29)
  - Cobb by Lee Blessing, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 30-37)
    Yale Repertory Theatre, 1989; Alliance Theatre Company, Atlanta, 1990; Old Globe Theatre, San Diego, 1990
    Includes correspondence with Stuart Hyke
  - Cobb by Lee Blessing, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 38-45)
  - The Committeeman by Joseph Stefano, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    CBS General Electric Theater (television)
  - The Crucible by Arthur Miller, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 47-49)
    Boston University, 1962
  - The Desperate Hours by Joseph Hayes, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 50-51)
  - A Doll's House by Henrik Ibsen, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 52-54)
    Yale Repertory Theatre, 1982
  - The Egghead by Molly Kazan, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 55-59)
  - An Enchanted Land by Dale Wasserman, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 60)
    New Federal Theatre, New York City, 1997
  - Fences by August Wilson
    Performed at National Playwrights Conference in 1983 (?); Yale Repertory Theatre, 1985; Goodman Theatre, Chicago, 1986; Seattle Repertory Theatre, 1986; James A. Dolittle Theatre, Los Angeles, 1988
    Includes correspondence with August Wilson regarding the 1997 Tony Awards and a performance of an excerpt.
    - National Playwright's Conference script, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 61)
    - Working scripts and August Wilson letters, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 62-63)
    - Yale Repertory production, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 64-67)
    - Yale Repertory production, 1985-1986 (Box 9, Folder 68-71)
    - Chicago production, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 72)
    - Contracts, 1986-1987 (Box 9, Folder 73-74)
      Includes correspondence between Richards and August and their respective lawyers regarding subsidiary rights disagreement
    - Seattle production, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 75-76)
    - San Francisco production, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 77-78)
    - San Francisco production, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 79-83)
    - New York Broadway production, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 84-86)
    - New York Broadway production, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 87-94)
    - New York Broadway production, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 95-99)
    - New York Broadway production, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 100-103)
    - Tony Awards, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 104-105)
    - Tony Awards, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 106-112)
    - Pulitzer Prize, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 113)
    - Publicity, 1985-1987 (Box 15, Folder 114-115)
    - Los Angeles production, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 116-123)
    - Rights, 1987-1989 (Box 15, Folder 124)
    - London production, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 125)
    - Ottawa and Calgary productions, 1991-1993 (Box 16, Folder 126-127)
    - Florida State University production, 1997 (Box 16, Folder 128-130)
  - Freeman by Phillip Hayes Dean, 1972-1977 (Box 16, Folder 131-133)
    Alternate title was "The Collapse of the Great I Am"
    Visions, KCET-TV, 1976 (television)
  - Freeman by Phillip Hayes Dean, 1972-1977 (Box 17, Folder 134-136)
  - Ghosts by Henrik Ibsen, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 137)
    Playhouse in the Park, Cincinnati, 1965
  - Gold Watch by Momoko Iko, 1974-1975 (Box 17, Folder 138-141)
  - Hedda Gabler by Henrik Ibsen, 1981-1982 (Box 18, Folder 142-147)
    Yale Repertory Theatre, 1981
  - The Hide-And-Seek Odyssey of Madeline Gimple by Frank Gagliano, 1969 (Box 18, Folder 148)
    For ProjectCreate, Connecticut School System, 1969
  - I Had A Ball by Jerome Chodorov, 1964 (Box 19, Folder 149-153)
    Martin Beck Theatre, New York City, 1964
  - Joe Turner's Come and Gone by August Wilson
    Stage Reading at National Playwrights Conference, 1984; Yale Repertory Theatre, 1986; Huntington Theatre Company, Boston, 1987; Seattle Repertory Theatre, 1987; Kreeger Theatre, Washington D.C., 1987; Old Globe Theatre, San Diego, 1988; Ethel Barrymore Theatre, New York City, 1988
    Original title was Mill Hand's Lunch Bucket
    - Mill Hand's Lunch Bucket, 1983-1984 (Box 19, Folder 154)
    - National Playwright's Conference script, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 155-156)
    - Working scripts and August Wilson letters, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 157-158)
    - Yale Repertory Theatre production, 1986 (Box 20, Folder 159-165)
    - Boston production, 1986-1987 (Box 21, Folder 166-168)
    - Production notes, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 169)
    - Seattle production, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 170-171)
    - Washington, D.C. production, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 172-173)
    - San Diego production, 1987-1988 (Box 21, Folder 174-176)
    - New York production, 1988 (Box 22, Folder 177-178)
    - Reviews, 1988 (Box 22, Folder 179-181)
    - General file, 1986-1988 (Box 22, Folder 182)
    - Contracts, 1986-1988 (Box 23, Folder 183-184)
    - Tony Awards, 1988 (Box 23, Folder 185)
    - Drama Desk Awards, 1988 (Box 23, Folder 186)
    - Letters of congratulations, 1988 (Box 23, Folder 187-190)
    - Letters of congratulations, 1988 (Box 24, Folder 191-198)
    - Research materials, undated (Box 25, Folder 199-201)
  - Johnny Bull by Kathleen Betsko, 1982 (Box 25, Folder 202-203)
  - Just Before Morning by Tom Olive, 1967 (Box 25, Folder 204)
    Eugene O'Neill Memorial Theater, 1966-68
  - Killing Time, 1977-1978 (Box 26, Folder 205)
  - Late Nite Mystery Theatre, 1973-1974 (Box 26, Folder 206)
    For Universal City Studios (television)
  - A Lesson From Aloes by Athol Fugard, 1980 (Box 26, Folder 207-208)
    Yale Repertory Theatre, 1980; Playhouse Theatre, New York City, 1980-81
  - A Lion and the Jewel by Wole Soyinka, 1977 (Box 26, Folder 209-211)
    New York City, 1977
    Includes correspondence with Hazel Bryant
  - The Long Dream by Ketti Frings, 1959-1960 (Box 26, Folder 212)
    Ambassador Theatre, New York City, 1960
    Includes correspondence with Cheryl Crawford
  - The Long Dream by Ketti Frings, 1959-1960 (Box 27, Folder 213-215)
  - Ma Rainey's Black Bottom by August Wilson
    Eugene O'Neill Memorial Theater, 1982; Yale Repertory Theatre, 1984; Cort Theatre, New York City, 1984-85; Broadway revival 2003
    - Early script, 1983 (Box 27, Folder 216)
    - Yale Repertory Theatre production, 1984 (Box 27, Folder 217-219)
    - New York production, 1984-1985 (Box 28, Folder 220-224)
    - Revival, 2003 (Box 28, Folder 225)
  - Madmen and Specialists by Wole Soyinka, 1970 (Box 28, Folder 226-227)
    Eugene O'Neill Memorial Theater, 1970
  - A Man Around the House by Joseph Julian, circa 1966 (Box 29, Folder 228)
  - Master Harold... and the Boys by Athol Fugard, 1982, 1989 (Box 29, Folder 229-232)
    Yale Repertory Theatre, 1982; Lyceum Theatre, New York City, 1982
    Includes correspondence with Athol Fugard
  - Me, Candido! by Brad Kearny, 1963-1964, undated (Box 29, Folder 233-234)
  - Medal of Honor Rag by Tom Cole, 1981-1982 (Box 29, Folder 235)
    For PBS American Playhouse, 1982
  - Medal of Honor Rag by Tom Cole, 1981-1982 (Box 30, Folder 236-238)
  - Miss Black America, 1969-1970 (Box 30, Folder 239-240)
  - The Moon Besieged by Seyril Schochen, 1962 (Box 30, Folder 241-244)
    Lyceum Theatre, New York City, 1962
    Includes previously unopened letter to Lorin Price
  - A Moon for the Misbegotten by Eugene O'Neill, 1991 (Box 31, Folder 245-247)
    Yale Repertory Theatre, 1991
  - Night Must Fall by Emlyn Williams, 1978 (Box 31, Folder 248)
    Hunter College, New York City, 1978
  - No Easy Walk To Freedom, 1979 (Box 31, Folder 249-252)
    Bill Moyer's Journal, PBS, 1979, WNET Thirteen (television)
  - Oedipus Rex by Sophocles, 1946 (Box 31, Folder 253)
    The Actor's Company, Detroit Repertory Theater, 1946
  - Othello by William Shakespeare, 1981
  - The Ox Cart (La Carreta) by Rene Marques, 1966-1967 (Box 32, Folder 254-257)
    Greenwich Mews Theatre, New York City, 1966-67
  - The Past is Past and Goin Thru Changes by Richard Wesley, 1973-1974 (Box 32, Folder 258-259)
    Billie Holiday Theatre, New York City, 1974
  - Paul Robeson by Phillip Hayes Dean
    PBS, 1970 (television). Film, 1977. Lunt-Fontanne Theatre, Booth Theatre, New York City, 1978; London, 1978; WETA26 1978 (television)
    - "Paul Robeson in Concert", undated (Box 32, Folder 260)
    - Scripts, 1977 (Box 32, Folder 261)
    - Scripts, 1977 (Box 33, Folder 262-264)
    - Program, 1977 (Box 33, Folder 265)
    - New York production, 1978 (Box 33, Folder 266-269)
    - New York production, 1978 (Box 34, Folder 270-274)
    - Traveling productions programs, 1977-1978 (Box 34, Folder 275)
    - Album recording session, 1978 (Box 34, Folder 276)
    - London production, 1978 (Box 34, Folder 277-279)
    - Scripts, 1979 (Box 35, Folder 280-282)
    - Robeson TV Special, 1978-1979 (Box 35, Folder 283-284)
    - Publicity, 1977-1979
    - Paul Robeson, Negro, photocopy of book, undated (Box 35, Folder 285)
    - Television special videocassette agreements, 1986-1987 (Box 35, Folder 286)
  - The Piano Lesson by August Wilson
    Staged reading at the Eugene O'Neill National Playwrights Conference, 1987; Yale Repertory Theatre, 1987; Huntington Theatre Company, Boston, 1988; Goodman Theatre, Chicago, 1989; Old Globe Theatre, San Diego, 1989; Center Theatre Group, Ahmanson Theatre, Los Angeles, 1989; John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, Washington, D.C., 1989; later James A. Dolittle Theatre, 1990; Walter Kerr Theatre, New York City, 1990; Theatre on the Square, Marietta GA, 1991; other U.S. cities, 1991
    - Early script draft with note from August Wilson to Richards, 1987 (Box 36, Folder 287)
    - Yale Repertory Theatre production, 1987 (Box 36, Folder 288-290)
    - National Arts Week New Haven, 1987 (Box 36, Folder 291)
    - Boston production, 1987-1988 (Box 36, Folder 292-298)
    - Chicago production, 1988-1989 (Box 36, Folder 299-301)